<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC "-//IETF//DTD RFC 2629//EN"
                "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
          'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY UMA PUBLIC ''
          'http://kantarainitiative.org/confluence/display/uma/Home'>
    <!ENTITY UMAreqs PUBLIC ''
          'http://kantarainitiative.org/confluence/display/uma/UMA+Requirements'>
]>

<rfc category='std' ipr='trust200902' docName='draft-uma-core-v1-00.txt'>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc='yes' ?>
  <?rfc tocdepth='3' ?>
  <?rfc symrefs='yes' ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs='yes' ?>
  <?rfc compact='yes' ?>
  <?rfc subcompact='no' ?>
  <?rfc strict='yes' ?>

  <front>

    <title abbrev='UMA Scope Registration'>User-Managed Access (UMA) Scope Registration Protocol</title>

   <author fullname='Christian Scholz' surname='Scholz' initials='C' role='editor'>
      <organization>COM.lounge GmbH</organization>
      <address>
        <email>cs@comlounge.net</email>
        <uri>http://comlounge.net</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname='Maciej Machulak' surname='Machulak' initials='M'>
      <organization>Newcastle University</organization>
      <address>
        <email>m.p.machulak@ncl.ac.uk</email>
        <uri>http://ncl.ac.uk/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>    
    <author fullname='Eve Maler' surname='Maler' initials='E'>
      <organization>PayPal</organization>
      <address>
        <email>eve@xmlgrrl.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.paypal.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year='2010' />

    <abstract>
      <t>
	This specification defines the Scope Registration Protocol for
	User-Managed Access (UMA).  This protocol provides a method for a Host
	to register or update scopes with an Authorization Manager.
      </t>
      <t>
	This document is a product of the User-Managed Access Work Group of the
	Kantara Initiative. It is currently under active development. It has
	not yet been submitted to the IETF. The User-Managed Access Work Group
	operates under Kantara IPR Policy - Option Patent and Copyright:
	Reciprocal Royalty Free with Opt-Out to Reasonable And Non
	discriminatory (RAND) and the publication of this document is governed
	by the policies outlined in this option.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title='Introduction'>
      <t>
	The Scope Registration Protocol provides a method for a UMA Host to register
	scopes with an UMA Authorization Manager. 
      </t>
      <t>
	Scopes are basically simple strings which only have meaning to the Host and are
	completely transparent to the Authorization Manager. For instance a scope can
	be all photos of a Host being marked as "for family only" or all photos of a 
	certain resolution.
      </t>
      <t>
	Scopes are registered with an AM by the Host and can be revoked again at any time.
      </t>
      <t>
	Resources are bundled to scopes only on the Host side. The Authorization Manager never
	knows in advance which resource (and thus URI pointing to one) falls under which scope
	unless a request is made to a resource in which case the Host informs the Authorization
	Manager about the scopes it falls under. The Authorization Manager can then make
	a decision based on the scope information if access is granted or not.
      </t>
      <t>
	In order to do so, resource owners attach policies to scopes. This can be as simple as 
	being asked on every request or as complex as fulfilling a chain of claims. The resolution
	of those policy questions is out of scope for this specification though and is part of
	the UMA core protocol specification.
      </t>

      <section title='Notational Conventions'>
        <t>
          The key words 'MUST', 'MUST NOT', 'REQUIRED', 'SHALL', 'SHALL NOT', 'SHOULD', 'SHOULD
          NOT', 'RECOMMENDED', 'MAY', and 'OPTIONAL' in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in <xref target='RFC2119' />.
        </t>
        <t>
          This document uses the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) notation of
          <xref target='I-D.ietf-httpbis-p1-messaging' />. Additionally, the realm and auth-param
          rules are included from <xref target='RFC2617' />.
        </t>
        <t>
          Unless otherwise noted, all the protocol parameter names and values are case sensitive.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title='Terminology'>
        <t>
	  We use the same terminology as the UMA core protocol specification. 
          <list style='hanging' hangIndent='6'>
             <t hangText='Scope'>
              <vspace />
	      A scope is a string known to a Host describing a set of
	      resources. An Authorization Manager can add policies to those
	      scopes which are checked on resource access. Scopes additionally
	      have a description in order to explain it to the user. 
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title='Prerequisites'>
	<t>
	    In order for a Host to be able to register scopes with an
	    Authorization Manager it needs to fulfill the following
	    prerequisites:
	</t>
    	<t>
    	<list>
	    <t>
		The Host has obtained an access token from the Authorization
		Manager as explained in the UMA core protocol specification,
		step 1. It can use this token to use the scope registration API
		of the Authorization Manager.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		The Host has obtained an the URI of the scope registration API
		as part of the Authorization Manager's metadata as described in
		the UMA core protocol specification, step 1. 
	    </t>
	    <t>
		The Host has already defined scopes for itself. These are often
		derivable from the functionality of the Host. For instance a photo
		site could already have scopes defined like "photos only
		visible for my family", "photos in a certain group", "photos tagged
		with a certain tag". The Host needs to define unique strings for 
		those scopes.
	    </t>
    	</list>
    	</t>
    </section>
    <section title='Registering scopes'>
    	<t>
    	  The following substeps are performed in order for a Host to register scopes
	  with an Authorization Manager.
    	  <list style="numbers">
	    <t>
		The Host creates a JSON formatted document describing all the scopes
		it wishes to register or to delete. 
	    </t>
	    <t>
		The Host sends this document to the Authorization Manager's scope
		registration API, using the access token it obtained in step 1 of
		the UMA core protocol.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		The Authorization Manager acknowledges that it received the scopes.
	    </t>
    	  </list>
    	</t>
    	<section title="Preparing the scope registration document">
    	<t>
	    The Host collects all the scopes available to the user the Authorization
	    Manager's access token is valid for and creates a JSON document of the 
	    following form:
    	</t>
	<figure>
	    <artwork>
<![CDATA[
    {
        'add' : [
                    {
                        'scope' : 'photos_family',
                        'desc'  : 'Photos available to my family',
                        'desc_de' : 'Fotos f&uuml;r meine Familie',
                    },
                    {
                        'scope' : 'group_fun',
                        'desc'  : 'Funny Photos',
                    }
                ],
        'delete' : ['photos_private']
    }
]]>
	    </artwork>
	</figure>
	<t>
	    It lists all the scopes it wished to be added with a description (optionally in multiple languages) 
	    in the section "add" and it lists all those (previously registered) scopes in the "delete" section
	    it wants to have deleted. In the latter case it only needs to list the scope names.

	    [[ add description of field names ]]
	</t>
	</section>
    
    	<section title="Host sending the Scope Registration document">
	    <t>
		The Host sends the crafted document to the Scope Registration API endpoint
		it obtained during metadata discovery. It uses the POST method to do so.

		[[ describe this further with examples ]]
	    </t>
	</section>
    	<section title="Authorization Manager sending a response">
	    <t>
		The Authorization Manager answers with a response containing "ok" in the case 
		of success or with an error message.

		[[ describe this further with examples and use some standard way to do so across the protocol]]
	    </t>
	</section>
    </section>
    <section title='Security Considerations'>
      <t>
	Who needs security anyway these days?
      </t>
    </section>

    <appendix title='TODOs'>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            TBS
          </t>
       </list>
      </t>
    </appendix>
    <appendix title='Acknowledgements'>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            TBS
          </t>
        </list>
        [[ Add further WG contributors ]]
      </t>
    </appendix>

    <appendix title='Document History'>
      <t>
        [[ to be removed by RFC editor before publication as an RFC ]]
      </t>
    </appendix>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>
    
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2617.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5785.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-hammer-hostmeta-13.xml'?>
      
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-httpbis-p1-messaging-09.xml'?>

<!--

      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2045.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2104.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2818.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3023.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3447.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4627.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-html401-19991224.xml' ?>
-->
    </references>

  </back>

</rfc>
